<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xinclude="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="media">
	<title>Publishing digital media</title>
	
	<para>
		The Research &amp; Education Space will not directly consume or publish digital media (audio, video, images,
		documents) itself. However, it will aggregate data <emphasis>about</emphasis>
		digital media which has been published in a form which can be used consistently
		by applications built on the platform.
	</para>
	<para>
		This chapter describes how those media assets can be published in ways which will be
		most useful to applications, while balancing the range of access mechanisms and
		rights restrictions applicable to users in educational settings.
	</para>
	<para>
		While this chapter provides guidance on publishing media assets themselves, those
		assets only become useful to within the Research &amp; Education Space when they are properly described
		in accompanying metadata. For more information on publishing data which describes
		digital media assets, please refer to the chapter <citetitle><link xlink:href="#assets">Describing digital assets</link></citetitle>.
	</para>
	
	
	<section xml:id="media-publication">
		<title>Approaches to publication</title>
		<para>
			There are three strategies for publishing media for the Research &amp; Education Space:
			<link xlink:href="#media-direct">publishing “raw” media assets</link>,
			providing <link xlink:href="#media-frame">embeddable players</link>,
			and publishing <link xlink:href="#media-page">pages which
			include playback capabilities</link>.
		</para>
		
		<tip>
			<para>
				A media publisher may make use of any or all of these strategies, possibly combined
				with access-control mechanisms where rights or other legal restrictions require it.
			</para>
		</tip>
		
		<section xml:id="media-direct">
			<title>Publishing media directly</title>
		
			<para>
				Publishing media directly is most suited to situations where the media assets
				are openly-licensed and can be both downloaded and streamed by
				applications. It is not suitable for media which is rights-restricted to the
				extent that downloads are not permitted.
			</para>
			<para>
				Direct publishing allows an application to make use of native playback,
				viewing, editing, and tagging capabilities, and consequentially offers the
				greatest level of flexibility to applications and users alike. While it provides
				no technical barrier to end-users <emphasis>sharing</emphasis> downloaded media
				(in whole or part on its own, or combined into a larger composition), it does
				not automatically imply that sharing is permitted.
			</para>
			<para>
				While affording the greatest level of flexibility to the consuming application,
				publishing media in this way is also the simplest from a technical perspective: the
				encoded media files are simply uploaded to a web server and then
				<citetitle><link xlink:href="#assets">described in the accompanying metadata</link></citetitle>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Use direct publication where:—
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Licensing allows both streaming <emphasis>and</emphasis> download of
						the media asset.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If you want to allow snipping or other kinds of editing of the media.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						You want to provide the widest possible range of device support.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>For example:—</para>
			
			<segmentedlist>
				<segtitle>Property</segtitle>
				<segtitle>Value</segtitle>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Media asset URL</seg>
					<seg><uri><link xlink:href="//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a4/Claude_Monet_1899_Nadar_crop.jpg">//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a4/Claude_Monet_1899_Nadar_crop.jpg</link></uri></seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>MIME type</seg>
					<seg><constant>image/jpeg</constant></seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Embeddable?</seg>
					<seg>Yes</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Poster image URL</seg>
					<seg><uri><link xlink:href="//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/Claude_Monet_1899_Nadar_crop.jpg/180px-Claude_Monet_1899_Nadar_crop.jpg">//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/Claude_Monet_1899_Nadar_crop.jpg/180px-Claude_Monet_1899_Nadar_crop.jpg</link></uri></seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Width</seg>
					<seg>2021px</seg>
				</seglistitem>

				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Height</seg>
					<seg>2694px</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Title</seg>
					<seg>Claude Monet 1899 Nadar crop</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>License</seg>
					<seg><link xlink:href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Public_domain">Public domain</link></seg>
				</seglistitem>
			</segmentedlist>
			
		</section>
	
		<section xml:id="media-frame">
			<title>Embeddable players</title>
			<para>
				Embeddable players are best suited to situations where media files should
				not be downloaded by applications and end-users, but the playback capability
				may be provided in-line with other content by an application.
			</para>
			<para>
				With an embeddable player, although media assets themselves are published in
				some fashion, the resource described in accompanying metadata is a web page
				capable of playing them, typically via an <tag class="element">iframe</tag>
				or equivalent, with the metadata including the preferred dimensions of the
				frame.
			</para>
			<para>
				This approach limits the capabilities which can be offered by the application
				to its users: as far as the application is concerned, the contents of the
				framed web page are completely opaque; it can only assume that the page
				will provide a suitable player for the media asset, and will have no
				control over playback.
			</para>
			<para>
				Use an embeddable player where:—
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Licensing only permits streaming of the asset, but
						<emphasis>does</emphasis> allow its presentation as part of a larger
						body of content (for example, within in a MOOC).
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Media is only available through a technology which
						may not be widely supported except through a custom player.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Your media is published through a third party solution which does
						not provide ready access to direct media asset URLs.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						As a fall-back option alongside a direct media link (for example,
						to enable an application to generate the embeddable player code
						snippet for pasting into a MOOC or social network).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>For example:—</para>
			
			<segmentedlist>
				<segtitle>Property</segtitle>
				<segtitle>Value</segtitle>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Media asset URL</seg>
					<seg><uri><link xlink:href="//player.vimeo.com/video/110040373">//player.vimeo.com/video/110040373</link></uri></seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>MIME type</seg>
					<seg><constant>text/html</constant></seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Embeddable?</seg>
					<seg>Yes</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Poster image URL</seg>
					<seg><uri><link xlink:href="//i.vimeocdn.com/video/494149068_960.jpg">//i.vimeocdn.com/video/494149068_960.jpg</link></uri></seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Preferred width</seg>
					<seg>500px</seg>
				</seglistitem>

				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Preferred height</seg>
					<seg>281px</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Title</seg>
					<seg>Mount Piños Astrophotography Time Lapse</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Duration</seg>
					<seg>45s</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>License</seg>
					<seg><link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons 3.0 Unported (CC BY 3.0)</link></seg>
				</seglistitem>
			</segmentedlist>
			
		</section>
	
		<section xml:id="media-page">
			<title>Stand-alone playback pages</title>
			<para>
				Stand-alone playback pages provide the least flexibility to
				applications, and—depending upon presentation—may result in reduced
				visibility of your media.
			</para>
			<para>
				With this strategy, an application is not able to embed your media
				at all, but instead must navigate to the page that you provide in
				a browser window. The application might provide a thumbnail or text
				link to your playback page, or it might choose to omit the media
				altogether if including it would result in a poor user experience.
			</para>
			<para>
				Use a stand-alone playback page where:—
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Licensing restrictions mean that you’re not able to authorise
						any kind of embedding.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						As a fall-back option alongside an embeddable player or direct
						media links (particularly if you already publish a playback page
						for each media asset).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>For example:—</para>
			
			<segmentedlist>
				<segtitle>Property</segtitle>
				<segtitle>Value</segtitle>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Media asset URL</seg>
					<seg><uri><link xlink:href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/p0285z2y/horizon-19811982-the-race-to-ruin">http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/p0285z2y/horizon-19811982-the-race-to-ruin</link></uri></seg>
				</seglistitem>

				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Title</seg>
					<seg>Horizon: 1981-1982: The Race to Ruin</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Embeddable?</seg>
					<seg>No</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Duration</seg>
					<seg>48m52s</seg>
				</seglistitem>
				
				<seglistitem>
					<seg>Geographical restriction</seg>
					<seg>UK-only</seg>
				</seglistitem>

			</segmentedlist>
			
		</section>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="media-acl">
		<title>Access control and media availability</title>
		
		<para>
			A key aim of the Research &amp; Education Space is to increase the visibility of and access to
			digital media resources which are available to staff and students of
			educational establishments within the United Kingdom. While this naturally
			includes the wealth of resources which are openly-licensed and available to
			everybody, it also includes digital media which can <emphasis>only</emphasis>
			be accessed at scale by UK educational users.
		</para>
		<para>
			In order to provide access to this material, publishers typically implement
			some kind of access control. While the platform itself is generally
			agnostic to media assets and their access-control mechanisms,
			applications require the ability to make user-interface decisions based upon
			the access restrictions imposed upon the media.
		</para>
		<para>
			For this reason, the Research &amp; Education Space defines three specific kinds of access-control mechanism,
			as well as a policy which conformant media must be published according to.
			Specifically, this policy is that media assets must:—
		</para>
		
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Media must be available either freely or under the terms of a blanket
					or statutorily-backed licensing scheme available to educational
					establishments (or licenses may be obtained on their behalf by local
					authorities or central government).
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					It must be possible to obtain the media without further subscription
					or other charges, however “value-added” services may be provided
					which offer additional capabilities (such as archiving, enhanced search),
					provided those services can be readily subscribed to at an establishment
					level.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The media must be generally available on a long term basis. Media available
					only for short periods has limited value in education because it prevents
					the same resources being used again in the future.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The technical access-control mechansims must be one or more of those
					described below.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The nature of the access-control mechanism must be described in the
					metadata accompanying the media.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		
		<para>
			For example, all of the following conform to the policy:—
		</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Media published via Wikimedia Commons is available to
					everybody on a permanent basis without any additional payment or subscritpion.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Programmes which are part of <link xlink:href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/bbcfour/collections">BBC
					Four Collections</link> are made available to everybody in the UK on a long-term basis
					(but may not be embedded). Access control is implemented through
					<link xlink:href="#media-geo">geo-blocking</link>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Recordings of broadcasts made according to the terms of <link xlink:href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1988/48/section/35">Section
					35 of the Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 1988 (as amended)</link> is
					may be used by the institution who recorded it (or it was recorded on
					behalf of), provided their <link xlink:href="http://www.era.org.uk">ERA Licence</link>
					is maintained.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Services which are authorised by ERA to maintain an archive of Section 35 recordings
					and make them available to ERA Licence-holders who pay a subscription fee, provided
					access is through a mechanism described below.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A consortium of rights-holders who together define a scheme for access to one or
					more sets of media on an affordable establishment-level subscription basis, provided 
					access is through a mechanism described below.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>
			For more information about describing rights restrictions and access-control mechansims,
			see <citetitle><link xlink:href="#rights">Metadata describing rights and licensing</link></citetitle>
			and <citetitle><link xlink:href="#conditional-access">Describing conditionally-accessible resources</link></citetitle>.
		</para>
		
		<section xml:id="media-geo">
			<title>Geographical restrictions (geo-blocking)</title>
			<para>
				Geo-blocking is the automatic determination of ability-to-access a resource
				by looking up the end-user’s public IP address against a database correlating
				IP address ranges with countries. For example, the address 132.185.240.10 is
				part of a range which is within the UK, whereas 192.0.32.8 is part of a range
				which is within the US.
			</para>
			<para>
				Geo-location databases and live services are available both for free and on
				commercial terms, with varying levels of quality and service assurance.
			</para>
			<para>
				Geo-blocking should generally be applied only where other access-control mechanisms are
				not applicable: for example, because a media asset is available to everybody
				within a particular country.
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="media-saml">
			<title>Federated access control using Shibboleth and the UK Access Management Federation</title>
			<para>
				<link xlink:href="https://shibboleth.net">Shibboleth</link> is a federated authentication
				single sign-on mechanism which is widely used by providers of materials
				to provide access only to staff and students of educational establishments.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <link xlink:href="http://www.ukfederation.org.uk">UK Access Management Federation</link>,
				operated by <link xlink:href="http://www.jisc.ac.uk/janet">Janet</link>, provides the
				Shibboleth federation for UK institutions.
			</para>
			<para>
				Shibboleth-protected resources present a sign-in page to users who are not already
				authenticated, which makes it suitable for use with both the embeddable player and
				the stand-alone playback page publication approaches described above.
			</para>
			<para>
				Shibboleth-based access control is the preferred mechanism for use where media should be
				made available only to educational users.
			</para>
		</section>
		
		<section xml:id="media-ipacl">
			<title>IP-based access control</title>
			
			<para>
				IP-based access control is often the simplest mechanism to implement, as it requires
				only for the publisher to check the end-user’s public IP address against a white-list
				and allow or permit access as required.
			</para>
			<para>
				However, creating and maintaining that white-list can involve significant administrative
				burden, particularly on a nation-wide basis, and it does not allow ready access to
				media to remote-working staff and students without their institution providing
				additional infrastructure such as remote-desktop services and VPNs.
			</para>
			<para>
				IP-based access control should generally be employed alongside Shibboleth-based
				authentication, and only for specific institutions which are not able to participate
				in the UK Acesss Management Federation.
			</para>
		</section>
		
	</section>
</chapter>
