<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xinclude="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="describing-consuming">
	<title>Describing and consuming data</title>

	<para>
	  The Research &amp; Education Space works on the basis that publishers
	  of data consumed by the platform and product developers using the API
	  both use the same sets of terms (vocabularies). If a publisher uses
	  a predicates tha aren't supported by a product, then that data is
	  essentially invisible to that product, resulting in a poor user
	  experience.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Rather than attempt to describe a vocabulary which includes the classes
	  and predicates needed to describe any conceivable kind of entity,
	  the approach taken by the Research &amp; Education Space is to identify
	  those which are already in common usage and document them: for many
	  publishers, this means that what they are already doing is entirely
	  sufficient (or requires only very minor changes), while for product
	  developers the amount of special-casing required to deal with data
	  indexed by the Research &amp; Education Space platform is kept to a
	  minimum.
	</para>
	<para>
	  This chapter contains the recommended approaches to describing
	  different kinds of entity. Data publishers should read it as our
	  recommendations for how those entities should be described (although
	  publishers are always free to include <emphasis>additional</emphasis>
	  data not covered by our recommendations). Product developers should
	  read the chapter as being a description of how they ought to expect
	  the data which is surfaced by the platform to be structured.
	</para>

	<xi:include href="common.xml" />
	<xi:include href="assets.xml" />
	<xi:include href="concepts.xml" />
	<xi:include href="media.xml" />
	<xi:include href="creative.xml" />
	<xi:include href="things.xml" />
	<xi:include href="people.xml" />
	<xi:include href="places.xml" />
	<xi:include href="events.xml" />
	
</chapter>