<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xinclude="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="editorial-guidelines-for-content-providers">
	<title>Editorial Guidelines for Content Providers</title>
	<para>
		What do we mean by “editorial”?
	</para>
	<para>
		In this context we mean what is <emphasis>in</emphasis> the metadata and the associated media, such as text, video or images. 
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>What does it say and what is it about?</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Is it suitable for all ages to see and hear?</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Are there any limits you would want to set around who could see this material?</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
		When making metadata and media available in to education, it is important to understand the expectations of the users in terms of what they will see and hear.
	</para>
	<para>
		These guidelines are intended to help content providers think about these issues as early in the process as possible.
	</para>
	<para>
		The RES platform is funded with public money and needs to show that it is serving the public interest and behaving responsibly.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Some items in physical collections are only available to certain users.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>How is this information transferred to the online catalogue?</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Are there items in your collections which you believe are not suitable for under-18s?</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>How will you help end users know this?</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>The RES proposal intends that in schools, the primary users of the products built on the RES aggregator will be teachers.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>But teachers are over-worked and are more likely to use your material if it is easy and quick to identify as relevant to their students.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>If you hold any data or guidance on age suitability you should include this in the data you publish.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Users will be able to feedback to you about concerns with the metadata or assets, including possible breach of copyright – how will you as an institution manage this?</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Although you will probably already have a mechanism for dealing with feedback and/or requests of either a legal (copyright, data protection etc) or editorial nature, it is worth being aware that RES may expose your material to a wider audience and these requests may therefore increase. Can your existing workflows manage this?</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>In sharing data and assets are you comfortable that you are complying with the <link xlink:href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1998/29/contents">Data Protection Act</link>.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</chapter>