<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<section version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="search">
  <title>Search for entities</title>
  <para>
	Where searching is available within a dataset (including the root), the
	<literal>osd:template</literal> will be present, providing an
	<link xlink:href="#opensearch">OpenSearch template</link> which can be
	populated with query parameters. The most important parameters are
	described below for reference.
  </para>
  <note>
	<para>
	  At present, there is not a well-supported mechanism for fully 
	  describing the search capabilities as Linked Open Data, although we
	  are exploring possibilities in this area. In the meantime, applications
	  will most likely need to hard-code behaviours relating to certain
	  query parameters—but where possible should do so based upon their
	  presence within the OpenSearch template.
	</para>
  </note>
  <para>
	The <literal>q</literal> parameter is a free-text query field which can
	be used (often in combination with other parameters) to find entities
	whose name or description includes particular words.
  </para>
  <para>
	The <literal>class</literal> parameter restricts the query to only
	those entities which are of the specified class (e.g., <uri>http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/Agent</uri>).
  </para>
  <para>
	The <literal>media</literal> and <literal>type</literal>
	parameters are used to perform <firstterm>media-scoped</firstterm>
	queries: these restrict the results to entries which are indexed as
	having <emphasis>related media</emphasis> matching the given parameters.
  </para>
  <para>
  The <literal>for</literal> parameter expands the scope of the query,
  rather than restricts it, allowing extra related media to be included
  in addition to that which is available to the general public;
  </para>
  <para>
	The <literal>media</literal> parameter accepts either a URI within
	the <link xlink:href="http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/dcmi-type-vocabulary/">DCMI Type Vocabulary</link>, or one of the defined aliases:
	<literal>audio</literal>, <literal>collection</literal>, <literal>dataset</literal>, <literal>image</literal>, <literal>interactive</literal>, <literal>software</literal>, <literal>text</literal> and <literal>video</literal>, or the
	special value <literal>any</literal>.
  </para>
  <note>
	<para>
	  Web pages and data views are themselves a kind of media which may
	  be indexed by the platform, which may yield results which are
	  initially confusing. The <literal>media=any</literal> query can
	  be helpful for debugging, but has limited practical use in applications
	  for this reason.
	</para>
  </note>
  <para>
	The <literal>type</literal> parameter restricts results to entries which
	have related media of the specified MIME type. Note that the broad class of
	MIME type may differ from the media kind described above; for example,
	a video playback web page is a <literal>video</literal> which has a
	MIME type of <literal>text/html</literal>. Generally applications will
	not need to expose this filter to end-users.
  </para>
  <para>
	The <literal>for</literal> parameter expands the scope of the query,
	rather than restricts it: by default, a media query only includes results
	where the related media is available to general public; the
	<literal>for</literal> parameter causes the API to <emphasis>also</emphasis>
	include items whose related media is available only to the group of people
	identified by the specified URI. See <cite><citetitle><link xlink:href="#audience-groups">Discover known audience group URIs</link></citetitle></cite>
	for further details.
  </para>
</section>
