<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<section version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="determine-kind">
  <title>Determine the kind of entity that retrieved data describes</title>
  <para>
	Once you have retrieved data from the index about an entity
	(which might be the index itself), determining the type
	of the entity allows you to determine how that data should be
	presented and tailor further user journeys appropriately.
  </para>
  
  <para>
	The <literal>rdf:type</literal> properties in the data describing
	an entity represent the <emphasis>class</emphasis> or kind of
	entity being described. The platform will
	<link xlink:href="#class-index">automatically assign very broad classes</link>,
	but will also convey all of the classes which can be found in
	the source data.
  </para>
  
  <para>
	The example below shows the data held in the index about
	<uri>http://acropolis.org.uk/824ac9e32f8b48b48a54be3c069f95bc#id</uri>,
	which is the URI assigned by the platform for <firstterm>Jabal Karsh</firstterm>,
	a place in Saudi Arabia. The class <literal>geo:SpatialThing</literal>
	is assigned by the platform (because the aggregated data was determined
	when it was indexed to refer to a place). The class
	<literal>gn:Feature</literal> is also present, because one or
	more descriptions of the place in source data used this class.
  </para>
  
  <programlisting language="turtle"><![CDATA[<http://acropolis.org.uk/824ac9e32f8b48b48a54be3c069f95bc#id>
	a gn:Feature, geo:SpatialThing ;
	dct:isPartOf <http://acropolis.org.uk/7a811505b8304933b47f9ab6a90b9da8#id> ;
	olo:slot <http://acropolis.org.uk/824ac9e32f8b48b48a54be3c069f95bc#7a811505b8304933b47f9ab6a90b9da8> ;
	gn:locatedIn <http://acropolis.org.uk/e71507eb3c764e4a8a914a141672c512#id> ;
	rdfs:label "Jabal Karsh" ;
	rdfs:seeAlso <http://acropolis.org.uk/7a811505b8304933b47f9ab6a90b9da8#id> ;
	geo:lat 26.1 ;
	geo:long 39.65 .
]]></programlisting>
  <para>
	Once your application has determined which of the classes applies to the
	entity you’ve retrieved data about, it can determine how to proceed with
	processing the data further and presenting it. For example, when something
	is a place—as in the example shown above—it can look for geographical
	co-ordinates and show them on a map. Meanwhile, a dataset might be
	presented as a listing with search and refinement options.
  </para>
</section>
