<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<section version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="rights">
	<title>Understanding rights and licensing</title>

	<para>
		The Research &amp; Education Space aggregates data which can be
		re-used by a wide range of applications, and much of that data
		describes digital media (such as videos and photographs) which
		are accessible only to certain groups of people.
	</para>

	<para>
		To minimise the risk of data being incorporated into the index which
		applications cannot use, and to ensure an optimum user experience
		when querying for related media, RES requires that data included in the index
		includes accurate rights and licensing information.
	</para>

	<para>
		More specifically, for Linked Open Data to be indexed by the Research
    &amp; Education Space, it must be published under the terms of a
		<link xlink:href="#licenses">supported license</link> and include
		explicit licensing data. This approach is aligned with the Open Data Institute’s
		<link xlink:href="http://theodi.org/guides/publishers-guide-to-the-open-data-rights-statement-vocabulary">guide to publishing machine-readable rights data</link>.
		This means that any application which uses the RES index is
    using <emphasis>data documents</emphasis> which are openly-licensed.
	</para>

  <para>
    However, the data in the index will not necessarily contain rights
    statements about media (e.g. digital images, videos and audio), even if
    it contains rights statements about <emphasis>documents which describe</emphasis>
    that media. Consequently, applications which reuse media, either through
    embedding or linking, should not bypass any access controls on that media,
    to ensure that related access rights are not violated.
  </para>

	<tip>
	  <para>
		The Research &amp; Education Space was designed so that
		applications do not have to <emphasis>trust</emphasis> the
		platform regarding data licensing. As the crawler discriminates
		based upon the presence of explicit data licensing statements,
		an application can always verify those statements at
		source itself, using the same mechanisms employed by the crawler.
	  </para>
	</tip>
</section>
