<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xinclude="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="intro">
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
		The Research &amp; Education Space is powered by an <link xlink:href="https://bbcarchdev.github.io/res/code">open
		source software</link> stack named <firstterm>Acropolis</firstterm>,
		which is made of up three main components: a specialised web crawler,
		<firstterm>Anansi</firstterm>, an <firstterm>aggregator</firstterm>,
		<firstterm>Spindle</firstterm>, and a public API layer,
		<firstterm>Quilt</firstterm>. You can read more about the architecture
		of the stack in the section
		<cite><citetitle><link xlink:xhref="#architecture">Under the hood: the architecture of Acropolis</link></citetitle></cite>.
	</para>
	<para>
		<link xlink:href="https://github.com/bbcarchdev/anansi/">Anansi’s</link>
		role is to crawl the web, retrieving
		<link xlink:href="#licenses">permissively-licensed</link>
		<link xlink:href="#lod">Linked Open Data</link>, and passing it to the
		aggregator for processing. 
	</para>
	<para>
		<link xlink:href="https://github.com/bbcarchdev/spindle/">Spindle</link>,
		which is actually implemented as plug-in modules for our data workflow
		engine—<link xlink:href="https://github.com/bbcarchdev/twine/">Twine</link>—examines
		the data, looking for places where the same digital, physical
		or conceptual entity is described by Linked Open Data in more than one
		place, particularly where the data <link xlink:href="#sameas">explicitly states the equivalence</link>,
		and aggregates and stores that information in an index.
	</para>
	<para>
		This <link xlink:href="#structure"><firstterm>subject-oriented</firstterm> index</link> is the very heart of
		the Resarch &amp; Education Space: by re-arranging published data so
		that it's organised around the entities described by it, instead of by
		publisher or data-set, applications are able to rapidly locate all of
		the information known about a particular entity because it’s collected
		together in one place.
	</para>
	<para>
		<link xlink:href="https://github.com/bbcarchdev/quilt">Quilt</link> is
		responsible for making the index available to applications, also by
		publishing it as Linked Open Data. Because the Research &amp;
		Education Space maintains an <emphasis>index</emphasis>, rather than a
		complete copy of all data that it finds, applications must consume data
		both from the index and from the original data sources—and so the outputs
		from Quilt also conform to the publishing recommendations in this book.
	</para>
	<figure pgwide="1">
		<title>An overview of the Research &amp; Education Space</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="res-architecture.svg" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>
		We will not be directly developing end-user applications as part of
		the Research &amp; Education Space itself, although sample code and
		demonstrations have been published (<link xlink:href="http://res-project.tumblr.com/post/145608555223/inside-acropolis-how-to-unlock-the-archives">inside-acropolis-how-to-unlock-the-archives</link>, 
		<link xlink:href="http://res-project.tumblr.com/post/146940470153/interacting-with-res-in-php">
		interacting-with-res-in-php</link> and 
		<link xlink:href="http://res-project.tumblr.com/post/154464075083/what-does-res-do-with-your-data">
		what-does-res-do-with-your-data</link>) to assist software developers in
		doing so. There is also a “powered by RES” logo.
	</para>
		<figure pgwide="1">
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="powered-by-res-icon-green-text.jpeg" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>
		The Research &amp; Education Space only indexes and publishes data which
		has been released under terms which permit re-use in both commercial
		<emphasis>and</emphasis> non-commercial settings, so that all kinds of
		applications can be developed using the platform.Go to our Blog (
		<link xlink:href="http://res-project.tumblr.com/post/143892270473/open-data-the-digital-equivalent-of-letting">open-data-the-digital-equivalent-of-letting</link> and 
		<link xlink:href="http://res-project.tumblr.com/post/144859969193/the-pros-and-cons-of-open-licensing-vs">
		the-pros-and-cons-of-open-licensing</link>) to find out more on issue of licensing.
	</para>
	<para>
		For the Research &amp; Education Space to be most useful, holders of
		publicly-funded archive collections across the UK should publish Linked
		Open Data describing their collections (including related digital assets,
		where they exist). Although many collections are already doing so or
		plan to, the Research &amp; Education Space technical team will be
		providing tools and advice to collection-holders in order to assist them.
		Go to our blog (<link xlink:href="http://res-project.tumblr.com/post/151930243658/why-publish-modes-records-as-linked-data">why-publish-modes-records-as-linked-data</link>) to find out how one collection holder has made their data compatible with RES.
	</para>
</chapter>
