<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<section version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sameas">
  <title>Expressing equivalence with other identifiers</title>
  
  <para>
	Linked Open Data in general, and the Research &amp; Education Space
	in particular, is at its most useful when the data describing things
	links to other data describing the same thing.
  </para>
  
  <para>
	In RDF, this is achieved using the <literal>owl:sameAs</literal>
	predicate. This predicate implies a direct equivalence
	relationship—in effect, it creates a synonym.
  </para>
  	  
  <para>
	You can use <literal>owl:sameAs</literal> whether or not the
	alternative identifiers use <literal>http:</literal> or
	<literal>https:</literal>, although the practical usefulness of URIs
	which can’t resolved as Linked Open Data can be quite limited.
  </para>
  
  <para>
	For example, one might wish to specify that our book has an ISBN
	using the <literal>urn:isbn:</literal> URN scheme
	<citation><link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3187">RFC3187</link></citation>:
  </para>
  
  <programlisting language="turtle"><![CDATA[</books/9781899066100#id> owl:sameAs <urn:isbn:9781899066100> .]]></programlisting>
  
  <para>
	We can also indicate that the book described by our data refers to
	the same book at the British Library:
  </para>
  
  <programlisting language="turtle"><![CDATA[</books/9781899066100#id> owl:sameAs ]]>&lt;<link xlink:href="http://bnb.data.bl.uk/id/resource/011012558">http://bnb.data.bl.uk/id/resource/011012558</link>&gt; .</programlisting>
  
  <para>
	The outcome of this is that if an application queries the index
	for data about the entity identified as <uri>urn:isbn:9781899066100</uri>,
	any data describing the entity using <emphasis>your</emphasis>
	identifier, or the British Library’s, will also be aggregated by
	the index and returned.
  </para>
  
  <section xml:id="sameas-collections">
	<title>Tips for collection-holders</title>
	
	<para>
	  Asserting the equivalence between your own authoratitive
	  identifiers and <emphasis>well-known</emphasis> identifiers
	  for the same entity is an easy way to ensure that the Research
	  &amp; Education Space properly connects your information with
	  other people’s.
	</para>
	
	<note>
	  <para>
		Take care when using <literal>owl:sameAs</literal> to ensure
		that the subject and the object really are directly equivalent.
		In particular, make sure that you don’t accidentally state that
		somebody’s description of something (be it an HTML page or some
		other serialisation) is the same as the thing being described.
	  </para>
	</note>
	
	<para>
	  While you could look for equivalent identifiers managed by other
	  collections and make <literal>owl:sameAs</literal> assertions
	  about any you can find, this is likely to be wasted effort.
	  Instead, if everyone expresses the equivalence with the common
	  well-known identifier, the index will aggregate all of the
	  data from all of the collections which state equivalence with
	  that single identifier.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  Note that this doesn’t only apply to identifier schemes which
	  are formal standards: it works just as well with Wikidata URIs
	  as it does with ISBNs or GTINs.
	</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="sameas-developers">
	<title>Tips for application developers</title>
	
	<para>
	  When an application retrieves data from the index about an
	  entity, the Research &amp; Education Space includes information
	  about all of the identifiers it has encountered which refer
	  to that entity. This information is expressed as a series of
	  <literal>owl:sameAs</literal> statements where the subject is
	  the URI encountered in the source data, and the object is
	  the <literal>http://acropolis.org.uk/…</literal> URI that was
	  automatically assigned by the Research &amp; Education Space
	  platform.
	</para>
	
	<note>
	  If you retrieve quads, rather than triples, from the index,
	  these assertions are placed in a graph whose URI begins with
	  <literal>http://acropolis.org.uk/</literal>, because the
	  statements are generated by the platform itself and should
	  be distinguished from statements made in the source data.
	</note>
  </section>
  
</section>
