<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Author: Mo McRoberts <mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk>

 Copyright (c) 2014-2016 BBC

  Licensed under the terms of the Open Government Licence, version 2.0.
  You may obtain a copy of the license at:

	https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/version/2/

-->
<section version="5.0" xml:lang="en-gb" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="rights">
		<title>Rights and licensing</title>
		
		<para>
			The Research &amp; Education Space aggregates data which can be
			re-used by a wide range of applications, and much of that data
			describes digital media (such as videos and photographs) which
			are accessible only to certain groups of people.
		</para>
		<para>
			To minimise the risk of data being incorporated into the index which
			applications cannot use, and to ensure an optimum user experience
			when querying for related media, it's crucial that the data that
			collections publish includes accurate rights and licensing
			information.
		</para>
				
		<para>
			Linked Open Data must be published under the terms of a
			<link xlink:href="#licenses">supported license</link> and include
			explicit licensing data in order for it to be indexed by the
			Research &amp; Education Space and be useable by applications.
			Our approach is aligned with the Open Data Institute’s
			<link xlink:href="http://theodi.org/guides/publishers-guide-to-the-open-data-rights-statement-vocabulary">guide to publishing machine-readable rights data</link>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The Research &amp; Education Space crawler understands several common predicates for expressing the well-known URI of the license of a document:
		</para>
		
		<segmentedlist>
			<segtitle>Predicate</segtitle>
			
			<seglistitem>
				<seg><literal><link xlink:href="http://purl.org/dc/terms/license">dct:license</link></literal></seg>
			</seglistitem>

			<seglistitem>
				<seg><literal><link xlink:href="http://purl.org/dc/terms/rights">dct:rights</link></literal></seg>
			</seglistitem>
			
			<seglistitem>
				<seg><literal><link xlink:href="http://purl.org/dc/terms/accessRights">dct:accessRights</link></literal></seg>
			</seglistitem>
			
			<seglistitem>
				<seg><literal><link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/ns#license">cc:license</link></literal></seg>
			</seglistitem>
			
			<seglistitem>
				<seg><literal><link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#license">xhtml:license</link></literal></seg>
			</seglistitem>
			
			<seglistitem>
				<seg><literal><link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#copyright">xhtml:copyright</link></literal></seg>
			</seglistitem>
		</segmentedlist>
		
		<section xml:id="rights-rdf">
			<title>Simple licensing statements</title>
			<para>
				In many cases, the simplest way of expressing rights information 
				is to include it in the data that you're publishing, and this
				can often be accomplished by adding a single triple to each
				published documents using the <literal>dct:rights</literal>
				predicate or an equivalent (see above) predicates and a
				<link xlink:href="#licenses">supported license URI</link>.
			</para>
			<para>
				For data to be indexed by the Research &amp; Education Space,
				the crawler must be able to find (or derive) a licensing triple
				where the URL of the RDF document itself is the subject—essentially
				a triple which states “this document is licensed according to
				the terms identified by the following URI…”. In Turtle, this
				can be written as a triple similar to the below:
			</para>

			<programlisting language="turtle"><![CDATA[<> dct:license <http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/> .]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				This example assumes that you do not set <literal>@base</literal>,
				or if you do, that you don't set it to be anything other than
				the document’s own URL. If you do, you will need to be more
				specific in the subject of your licensing triple.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Publishers should also include similar triples for any digital
				assets that are referenced in the data which are licensed under
				a common set of terms. For example, if the data describes a set
				of images licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons
				Attribution License 4.0, then you should include triples
				indicating this.
			</para>
			<note>
				While the Research &amp; Education Space requires that ingested
				RDF data licensed under open terms, this requirement does
				<strong>not</strong> apply to digital assets <emphasis>described</emphasis>
				by that data.
			</note>

			<section xml:id="rights-rdf-example">
			  <title>Example</title>
		<para>
			The following example specifies that the Turtle representation of the data about our book is <link xlink:href="#licenses">licensed</link> according to the terms of the <citetitle>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International licence</citetitle>, using the host-relative URI identifying the specific representation.
		</para>
		
		<programlisting language="turtle"><![CDATA[</books/9781899066100.ttl> dct:license <http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/> .]]></programlisting>

			</section>
			
			<section xml:id="rights-rdf-collections">
				<title>Tips for collection-holders</title>
				<para>
					It is important that the subject of this triple is the URI of the
					<emphasis>concrete document</emphasis>. If you have different URIs
					for each RDF representation, and either send a
					<literal>Content-Location</literal> header or redirect to them,
					you need to ensure that the subject of the licensing triple is
					representation-specific URI (e.g., <literal>/books/9781899066100.ttl</literal>).
				</para>
				<para>
					This is because the Research &amp; Education Space crawler is
					<emphasis>stateless</emphasis>, just like the underlying HTTP
					protocol itself. In practice, this means that when a document is
					being processed by the crawler, the only information which can
					be used to evaluate it is the <varname>request-URI</varname>,
					the <literal>Content-Location</literal> (if provided), any
					<link xlink:href="#rights-link">Link headers</link> that were
					sent, and the serialised RDF itself.
				</para>
				<important>
					<para>
						Most importantly, you cannot assume when you construct your RDF that the crawler (or any other HTTP client) will be aware of any alternative URIs which redirect to
						your document (for example, via a <literal>303 See Other</literal> redirect), and so although you can include triples about those URIs in the document, they
						will have no role in determining whether the licensing is suitable for use in the Research &amp; Education Space.
					</para>
				</important>
			
				<para>
					For publishers for whom publishing a licensing triple in each
					document is difficult (for example because it involves adding a
					large number of triples to a store due to the nature of the
					publication workflow), there are alternative—equivalent—mechanisms
					described in the <cite><citetitle><link xlink:href="#explicit-licensing">Publishing data for the Research &amp; Education Space</link></citetitle></cite>
					part of this book.
				</para>
			
				<para>
					If you need to, you can provide more information than the license triple alone. For example, you might include a <emphasis>request</emphasis> which is not a formal requirement of the licensing terms, but you would like consumers to adhere to if possible.
				</para>
				<para>
					One way to do this is to include a <literal>dct:license</literal> triple referring to the well-known license URI, alongside a <literal>dct:rights</literal> triple pointing to a locally-defined <literal>odrs:RightsStatement</literal> entity (described using the <link xlink:href="http://schema.theodi.org/odrs/">Open Data Rights Statement Vocabulary</link>).
				</para>
			</section>

			<section xml:id="rights-rdf-developers">
			  <title>Tips for application developers</title>
			  <para>
				The Research &amp; Education Space was designed such that
				applications do not have to <emphasis>trust</emphasis> the
				platform regarding data licensing. As the crawler discriminates
				based upon the presence of explicit data licensing statements,
				an application is always able to verify those statements at
				source itself using the same mechanisms employed by the
				crawler.
			  </para>
			</section>		

		</section> <!-- #rights-rdf -->
		

<!--		
		<para>
			See the <link xlink:href="#document-metadata">Metadata describing documents</link> section for further details on describing individual RDF representations.
		</para>
		
	</section> -->
	
		<section xml:id="conditional-access">
			<title>Conditionally-accessible resources</title>

			<para>
				Many kinds of resource are not available to the general
				public but may be accessed by the key audience of the Research
				&amp; Education Space: students and teachers affiliated with
				a recognised educational institution in the UK. This may be
				because specific exceptions in law allow access when it would
				not otherwise be possible, or because the rights-holder has
				elected to make the assets available only to those in
				formal education.
			</para>
			<para>
				In order to support this, and ensure that users of RES
				applications are able to use to the greatest range of
				material that they legitimately have access to, the metadata
				describing those assets which aren’t available to the public
				but are to educational users must describe means by which
				they are accessed.
			</para>
		
			<tip>
				<para>
					A given asset may be available from multiple sources,
					each with its own specific constraints applied to who 
					may access it. For example, a recording of a radio
					programme might be held on behalf of educational users by
					two separate online services, both requiring that the
					affiliated institution be a licensee of the relevant
					<link xlink:href="http://www.era.org.uk">ERA licensing scheme</link>,
					and both operating their own institutional-level
					subscription schemes. To be most useful, the index
					must aggregate the metadata describing
					<emphasis>both</emphasis> means of access, and the
					metadata must convey sufficient information so as
					to allow applications to decide which, if any, should be
					presented to the end-user.
				</para>
			</tip>

			<para>
			  Conditional access is described by publishing the following data:
			</para>
			
			<itemizedlist>
			  <listitem>
				<para>
				  Assigning a URI to the group of people who may access the
				  resource, known by the Research &amp; Education Space
				  as an <firstterm>audience URI</firstterm>.
				</para>
			  </listitem>				  
			  <listitem>
				<para>
				  A rights statement, which uses the
				  <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/ns/odrl/2/">ODRL vocabulary</link>
				  to grant <emphasis>conditional</emphasis> permission to
				  access the resources the statement is associated with.
				</para>
			  </listitem>
			  <listitem>
				<para>
				  Using one of the rights predicates described above to
				  associate an actual resource with the rights statement.
				</para>
			  </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>
			  When this data is processed, the Research &amp; Education Space
			  indexes the fact that the resource is conditionally-accessible
			  and the URI assigned to the group of people who have permission
			  to access it.
			</para>

			<tip>
			  <para>
				Where multiple publishers participate in a scheme using
				a common authentication mechanism to grant access to the
				same set of users, they should agree to use the same
				audience URI to identify those users.
			  </para>
			</tip>

			<para>
			  Applications can then use this URI when performing queries in
			  order to include restricted resources in the results.
			</para>
			
			<section xml:id="conditional-access-example">
			  <title>Example</title>
			  <para>
				The following example excerpt describes two <link xlink:href="#creative">episodes of television programmes</link>,
				and their associated media players (see <cite><citetitle><link xlink:href="#av">Audio, video, and images</link></citetitle></cite>) which are
				both accessible only to authorised users of the
				<link xlink:href="http://shakespeare.ch.bbc.co.uk">BBC Shakespeare Archive Resource</link>.
			  </para>

			  <programlisting language="turtle"><![CDATA[<http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/programmes/PCDD329F#id> a po:Episode ;
	rdfs:label "Arall Fyd"@cy-gb ;
	mrss:player <http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/programmes/PCDD329F/player> .

<http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/programmes/LRPI646P#id> a po:Episode ;
	rdfs:label "Five to Eleven - Cyril Luckham"@en-gb ;
	mrss:player <http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/programmes/LRPI646P/player> .

<http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/programmes/PCDD329F/player>
	dct:format <http://purl.org/NET/mediatypes/text/html> ;
	dct:license <http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/terms#id> ;
	a dcmitype:MovingImage .

<http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/programmes/LRPI646P/player>
	dct:format <http://purl.org/NET/mediatypes/text/html> ;
	dct:license <http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/terms#id> ;
	a dcmitype:MovingImage .

<http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/terms#id>
	a odrl:Policy ;
	rdfs:label "Accessible only by authorised users in formal education in the UK"@en-gb ;
	odrl:permission <http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/terms#play> .

<http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/terms#play>
	a odrl:Permission ;
	odrl:action odrl:play ;
	odrl:assignee <http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/#members> .

<http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/#members>
	a odrl:Group ;
	rdfs:label "Authorised users of the BBC Shakespeare Archive Resource"@en-gb .

]]></programlisting>
			  <para>
				In the example above, the two <literal>po:Episode</literal>
				entities state that they have an embeddable media player
				using the <literal>mrss:player</literal> predicate. The data
				describing the two player URIs indicates that specific
				licensing terms apply to them, identified by the URI
				<uri>http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/terms#id</uri>, which
				is an <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/ns/odrl/2/ODRL21#term-Policy">ODRL Policy</link>.
			  </para>
			  <para>
				The policy statement includes a permission (identified as
				<uri>http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/terms#play</uri>,
				although the Research &amp; Education Space does not require
				an explicit URI to be assigned to each individual permission),
				which states that the action <literal><link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/ns/odrl/2/ODRL21#term-play">odrl:play</link></literal>
				may be performed by members of the group
				<uri>http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/#members</uri>.
			  </para>
			  <para>
				When this data is processed by the Research &amp; Education
				Space, the platform indexes the fact that these players are
				associated with their respective creative works, and that
				they are accessible only be members of the audience group
				which has the URI
				<uri>http://shakespeare.acropolis.org.uk/#members</uri>.
			  </para>
			</section>

			<section xml:id="conditional-access-collections">
			  <title>Tips for collection-holders</title>
			  <para>
				It is important to remember that the Research &amp; Education
				Space platform, and the applications which use its API, are
				not responsible for enforcing access control applied to
				resources that you publish. The mechanisms described here
				are used to describe the access restrictions that you already
				have in place so that user interfaces can properly account
				for them.
			  </para>
			  <para>
				In the absence of data to the contrary, the platform will
				assume that media resources are generally accessible to the
				public. Once data has been processed which describes access
				restrictions, the index is updated accordingly.
			  </para>
			  <para>
				Access restrictions are only recognised when they assign
				one of the ODRL actions <literal>odrl:play</literal>,
				<literal>odrl:present</literal>, <literal>odrl:display</literal>
				or <literal>odrl:use</literal> to an audience URI using the
				<literal>odrl:assignee</literal> predicate as part of an ODRL
				policy statement. Other forms of policy are not processed,
				and permissions related to other types of action are ignored.
			  </para>
			  <warning>
				<para>
				  The Research &amp; Education Space platform is not
				  able to fully process and index more complex policy
				  statements, for example those which grant permission to
				  an audience group but where that grant is subject to
				  additional restrictions—if this is expressed, the additional
				  restrictions will not be conveyed in the index, and end-user
				  applications may not be able to deal intelligently with
				  them. Such policies are best avoided.
				</para>
			  </warning>
			</section>		
			
			<section xml:id="conditional-access-developers">
			  <title>Tips for application developers</title>

			  <para>
				By default, the Research &amp; Education Space API will not
				include conditionally-accessible resources in results of
				queries. This means that when querying for concepts which
				have associated media, the default behaviour is to return
				those concepts whose associated media appears to be available
				to all.
			  </para>
			  
			  <para>
				In order to include conditionally-accessible resources in
				the results, an application must explicitly include the
				<literal>for</literal> parameter in <link xlink:href="#operations">its queries</link>,
				which specifies the URI of an audience group to include.
			  </para>
			  
			  <para>
				Applications should provide a mechanism for the user
				or administrator to specify which audience groups users
				are part of. Note that this doesn't grant or deny access
				to the resources themselves—that's the responsibility of
				the publisher of those resources—but is instead a mechanism
				for applications to hide from view those resources which are
				not accessible to the end-user.
			  </para>

			  <para>
				Information about the audience groups known to the
				platform can be retrieved from the
				<link xlink:href="#audience-groups"><literal>/audiences</literal></link>
				dataset. By periodically retrieving this dataset, applications
				can populate a list of audience groups for users or
				administrators to choose from.
			  </para>
			</section>

		</section> <!-- #conditional-access -->
		

</section>